welcome to the Hingham Board of
Selectmen meeting for Tuesday evening
January 30th 2018 we're actually coming
to you from the second floor and that's
because later in the evening we will be
joined by Hingham Advisory Committee and
our Community Preservation Committee who
will be preparing and reviewing their
recommendations for community
preservation funding for the next fiscal
year prior to that we do not have any
minutes for approval any public comment
on items not on the agenda okay if not
for for the next 45 minutes or so we
will be conducting three interviews for
police patrolmen positions we have three
candidates each candidate will come in
individually the board will have an
opportunity to ask some questions the
board will take up the appointment of of
the patrolman at our meeting next week
so chief and deputy chief you're ready
to go okay could you could you ask mr.
campanelle to come in please
mr. Campanella come on over
welcome Aaron power nice to meet you
welcome ask me oh yes sir Paul Healy mr.
Kamin if you want to take a seat right
over there thank you so much for coming
in this evening so this evening what
we're gonna do we're gonna take you know
10 10 or 15 minutes and the way we'd
like to structure this interview is give
you an opportunity first to introduce
yourself to the board tell us a little
bit about you and your interest in the
position and then each one of the three
of us will ask you a couple of questions
and then at the very end we'll give you
the opportunity to either ask us any
questions that you have or make any
additional points that you want to make
sure the board is aware of so that's
kind of the sequence for this evening if
you could start and tell us a little bit
about you sure good evening my name is
Derek campanelle
I was born and raised right next door
and all Massachusetts I grew up there
once a high school there graduated in
2006 from that point I went over to
Roger Williams University down in Rhode
Island and studied criminal justice I
earned a bachelor's degree and a
master's degree in criminal justice was
in school there I did a few internships
one with the Barnstable County Police
Department
and also one for the Massachusetts State
Police underwater recovery unit and
marine section after completing my
degrees at Roger Williams I moved back
to Noah and worked as a front desk clerk
for the police station there after about
a year or so doing that I ended up
taking a full-time police officer
position with the county of Maui on in
Hawaii attended a nine month intensive
Police Academy out there I was on the
road for a few months and just about at
the year mark of moving out
there I realized that I miss home so I
ended up coming back and I moved to hang
them from that point I went in attended
police academy at the Plymouth Reserve
Academy down in Plymouth and from that
point I've been working as a special
police officer for the Town Hall and
also as a front desk clerk for the
police station there and I've pretty
much been around Hingham all my life
huge into Revolutionary War Reenactment
on the 4th of July parade dressed as a
Redcoat reenactor and it's pretty much
my story thank you thank you on a day
like today you must miss Hawaii just a
little just a little bit just a little
bit Paul maybe you'd like to start with
a question or two sure mr. Campanella
here your accomplishments in my opinion
are impressive I noticed you also hold a
pilot's license yes sir that is correct
that what kind of what kind of plane a
you license to fly I'm licensed in
mostly small single-engine aircraft from
Cessnas to piper warriors and piper
archers I have about I think 140
pilot-in-command hours of those types of
aircraft and that was something that I
worked on while I was at school to try
to broaden my horizons all been and try
to teach me about communication skills
and multitasking and being able to talk
to air traffic control and fly a plane
and do everything all at once I think
that helped a little bit did you
complete the nine-month Academy that you
referenced in Hawaii
yes arigon alright and and did you do
any street work out there I completed
two full months of the FTO program out
there there was another two phases I
was in the process of completing but at
that point I realized that I miss
Massachusetts a lot I miss the community
being 13 hours by flight from my family
and friends and everything that I knew
it it just kind of came down a little
heavy on me and I realized that I still
wanted to be a police officer but I
don't want to continue their career up
there in Hawaii you have police officers
in your family yes sir who would that be
my my uncle is a written retired
lieutenant with the State Police
my older brother is a was a homicide
detective diamond Florida for 10 years
and he's currently with the FBI task
force out of Miami Florida my twin
brother is also a special police officer
for the Town Hall for a number of years
parents must be proud yes sir do you
have an opinion or do you hold one with
respect to the most significant battle
of the revolution in the southern parts
of the country I do I personally hold
the opinion I know that I believe it was
the Battle of Yorktown when they saw
under the sword was presented to a
Hingham resident by the name of Lincoln
okay thank you very much thank you sir
yeah yeah I would concur with my with my
colleague mr. Haley that you have a very
impressive resume mr. Campanella and I
just have a couple questions for you
sure I was particularly impressed with
your educational background you shared a
little bit about about that with with
all of us on with the public tonight I'm
just wondering in terms of your
education how do you think that that's
helped shape you as a candidate now for
a police officer job and hang them the
thing about my resume that I think is
helped quite a bit was I've gained a lot
of experience with a lot of differ
departments from County police agencies
like the Barnstable County Police
Department with a small town nor wall
that I'm very familiar with and then
with a large city department like that
out in Maui Hawaii I kind of can take
all those experiences and then add the
State Police experience and kind of
narrowed it down to I want something
bigger than Noel but not too big
something that can still be is a small
community
a community where you can know everyone
by name where you can see the same faces
over and over again kind of like a
community that you don't most see in a
Norman Rockwell painting or illustration
that's the type of Police Officer that I
want to be is one that knows the
community and is deeply tied with the
community rather than one that you never
see the same people twice but then at
the same time that the department's not
too small that there's no room for
moving up and waiting around in years
and I feel like you know your decision
to move back you're your answer just now
it seems like you place a high value on
the community around you and I think
that is a value shared by the the
Hingham Police Department you know
unfortunately the hangin Police
Department sees not only the Norman
Rockwell tableau hang them in the square
but you know a lot of other stuff going
on not only and hang them but around the
South Shore and you know that's why I
think we're so thorough in our hiring
process because you play a pivotal role
in terms of developing community trust I
think in in the department and in its
officers but also in enforcing the laws
and it's sort of a tough balance and I
wonder if you can talk a little bit
about you know how you how you would
pursue that balance that is a tough
balance but I believe the best way about
going about that would be
[Music]
the aspect of community policing and
being able to take a proactive approach
to policing not so with community
policing instead of just being
completely reactive to everything that
happens with the town with the residents
you can kind of educate people and you
can tie the community into the police
department so that way when police
officers come to the residence of some
home you're more familiar and able to
help the police officer then at the same
time you're going to be eliminating some
of the calls for service hopefully and
reducing hopefully fatalities from
automobile accidents with programs like
the designated driver program or the
safe by the adult program where you
courage people to be wearing seatbelts
and you teach them about that and that's
going to cut down quite a bit too great
and one one final question and you
touched on on this a little bit in your
discussion with Paul but you know again
the other thing that jumps out about
your resume I think is the number of
sort of different experiences that
you've had the kind of hobbies that you
pursued and I'm wondering if you can
either pull from one of those
experiences or think about a challenge
that you may have encountered in your
life that you have overcome that again
sort of shaped you as a person to be a
police officer in Hingham
one thing that comes to mind for some
reason when you ask that question is one
of my thoughts of the patrol shifts out
in Hawaii one day when we got into the
cruiser my FTO and myself and we started
our shifts and just all of a sudden we
realized that there was a spider about
the size of my hand that was on the
front windshield of the cruiser so we
both jumped out of the cruiser we put in
the park and we jumped out
the spiders out there they're not only
big but they're poisonous so if they
bite you your feet your hands will
swallow up you won't even know it until
you notice the injury but so we jumped
out of the cruiser and we're looking and
trying to figure out what to do and all
of a sudden the spider from the middle
of the dashboard just goes down in
between the two seats between myself and
the FTO so we're standing there totally
bewildered what to do and then all of a
sudden the police radio started going
off and we realized that even though we
have this big dilemma and we're both
terrified of spiders that the job still
goes on and if that radio is going and
someone needs a cruiser first some sorta
call for service
we both got back in that cruiser and for
the rest of the night we're just
thinking about that and it kind of
amplifies that when you're there to do
the job you're there to do the job and
no matter what happens while you're
there you're gonna get the job done
great thank you appreciate that thank
you ma'am I just have one final question
because some I think you've touched on a
number of different things and my
question is as you think about a Hingham
police officer and you think about the
qualities that that would be important
to be a successful police officer here
in Hingham what qualities jump to mind I
would say honesty compassion and being
humble is every person that you deal
with you need to bring all three of
those to the table and now even though
you're wearing a police officer's
uniform and that may make you feel a
little bit more brave and different and
you got to remember that every person
you're dealing with it could be a
veteran and they could be even braver
than you they could be a doctor
a really influential school educator and
you just need to bring that humility to
every call that you go to and even
though you're wearing the police officer
uniform you got to treat everyone with
utmost respect and dignity and the
honesty that that's completely probably
one of the most fundamental parts of
being a police officers your honesty and
integrity is um without that there's no
trust
and without respects every call you go
to you're going to be your own worst
enemy and you're going to be creating
problems rather than solving problems
mr. Campanella thank you very much thank
you and we will the board is we're
conducting the interviews this evening
and then next week we will be putting
this back on the agenda to make to make
decisions so again we so appreciate your
coming in this today thank you for
having me thank you
and so our next candidate is mr.
Benjamin car
welcome mr. pilot Karin Johnson there
was very power welcomed would you like
to take a seat right over there
mr. Carr thank you for coming in this
evening we're gonna take about 10 or 15
minutes we're gonna ask you to if you
could please lead off by introducing
yourself telling us a little bit about
your background telling us about why
you're interested in becoming a police
officer in the town of Hingham and then
each of us will take turns asking one or
two questions and then at the conclusion
we'll give you an opportunity to ask any
questions or make any any final remarks
that you'd that you'd like to so with
that I'll turn it to you for an
introduction please okay thank you very
much my name is Ben car I grew up in the
town of Hingham I graduated Hingham high
school in 2007 I went on to Stonehill
College where I graduated in to sorry I
graduated yeah graduated in 2011 from
Stone Hill
I majored in religious studies and
history since then I have worked in
higher education I did that for three
years at Curry College as an admissions
counselor probably my favorite position
that I've held thus far in my career but
I've also had the opportunity to work in
sales as well as working in advertising
and software at the moment the biggest
reason why I would like to be a hanger
police officer is I've always tried to
find the things in a career that enabled
me to have some sense of fulfillment
when I go home and I can't think of a
better place to be a police officer than
the town I grew up in a town that
basically helped raise me I was
fortunate enough to grow up in a very
close-knit neighborhood so to have the
opportunity to be a police officer and
hang them and give back to the town and
give back to the people who looked after
me when I was growing up would be an
honor for sure thank you Karen would you
like to start with a question or two for
mr. Carr not sure mr. Carr you know very
very impressive resume really impressive
work experience I'm wondering wondering
if you could talk a little bit about
your educational experience and how that
may help shape you as a candidate
between Hingham high and Stonehill
College sir what about your education do
you bring to the table as a hanger
police officer it's actually a really
relevant question for me I've been
reflecting a lot recently having gone to
the process and when I went to hang them
high school to pick on my transcript I
asked the woman who worked at the desk
if I could visit one of my old teachers
and this teacher had taken me to Ireland
when I was senior in college
sorry senior in high school and that had
really kind of kicked off this travel
bug with me which later led me to
studying in Ireland and then feeling
comfortable enough to take a risk and
having lived abroad but I definitely was
shaped by hang him high school law and I
was very grateful for that and I was
felt lucky enough that I was able to
connect with her to tell her how much of
an impact that she had for me you know
hang him high school was it gets a lot
of credit having worked in higher
education I've compared it to other
schools as part of my job and I do feel
that the the high school prepared me
very well I felt like I was a step ahead
once I got to college and particularly
with that abroad experience not in high
school not quite being on my own but
with a group and having that sense of
Independence I felt much more
comfortable once I got to college and
was able to challenge myself and more
public speaking roles whether it was a
tour guide or working rec sports games
or even as an official for n-c-double-a
volleyball matches I was pretty
comfortable standing in front of people
and making a decision feeling confident
in my decisions
and I carried a lot of that to my sort
of grooming through hanging high school
that's fantastic and you know good for
you for taking the opportunity to seek
out your teacher and say thank you I
feel like I feel like it's sometimes
easier not to not to go to that trouble
and I can only imagine how that faculty
member felt when when they saw you first
of all as a grown up guy second of all
you know coming in to say thank you
that's a tremendous gesture and sort of
jumping off from there you know as you
consider this position you know that the
role of a police officer and Hingham is
important not only for law enforcement
but to the community as a whole and I
wonder if you've thought about kind of
the role of community policing as you've
considered this job I have absolutely
working as an admissions counselor a big
part of my role was actually in sort of
helping to develop the community at the
college so that students would feel more
comfortable i sat on the Diversity
Committee as the admissions office
representative and we would do different
programs to you know help students feel
more comfortable students who were we
referred to them as multicultural
students other colleges called the
mulana but in order to create that
greater sense of community really make
it feel at home as a police officer I
know it is very important to you know
really be a face be someone that the
public can see you as get to know you so
that way if anything is happening they
feel comfortable calling you flagging
you down or even if it's something that
they're just thinking hey there's
something going on can I talk to you
about it building that trust within the
community is obviously something that I
was strived for and is obviously very
important as well great and one last
question is you know again looking at
some of your experiences your your work
experience your experience living in
Australia I'm wondering if there's
something in your professional
experience or in a challenge that you
may have encountered and overcome that
you think adds a dimension to your
candidacy as as a hanger police officer
I think like khauran role would probably
have the most challenges I came into my
current company at a very very much a
transitional period so helping that
company develop different procedures and
operational processes or processes in
order to make the workflow run smoother
be more effective more efficient and
ultimately more profitable that's really
been the biggest challenges establishing
those processes and making them work and
also documenting them as well
great thank you good evening how are you
get are you I'm all right
you see you went to school and Island
for a period I did yes I went to the
National University of Ireland in Galway
for about four months
nice tell me sir
when you served as an admissions
counselor at Curry College what were the
qualities that you look for in students
and do you see any parallels in your own
candidacy for the position of the Leafs
officer here in Ingham yes I absolutely
see parallels one of the biggest things
I looked for in a student working at
curry it was a different student
population that we attracted then this
thence don't know where I went we were
getting students who had struggled in
high school often times we had a very
strong support program for students with
language based learning style of
differences so a lot of those students
hadn't had the support that they really
needed in order to succeed in high
school and we found a lot of the
students would do very well once they
got that support structure and actually
learned how they learned best so for me
a big thing was whether or not a student
was hardworking you know if a student
was excited about the opportunity to go
to college or if they felt like they
were just going through the motions
because that's what they were expected
of them and also I wanted to see
students who would improve throughout
their high school career and obviously
someone who's involved as well someone
who's gonna really add to that community
I've always been a hard worker I don't
know if you folks have my resume I think
I've had two jobs consistently since
I've worked consistently since I was 16
and you know I've always been someone
who's strive to improve no matter what
I've done whether it was working in a
pizza place when I was in high school
learning all the different roles within
that that restaurant from just cleaning
being a server working in the kitchen to
doing inventory all the things that then
led me to eventually run that restaurant
so I do think that
I guess selfishly looked for students
who had similar qualities to myself
because I felt like I had done well in
life and I knew the students had those
qualities they would also do well one
last question sir I noticed from your
application that you majored in
religious studies so I want to pose a
question to you joy at West Point is a
there's a monument of sort with with the
inscription a cadet will not lie cheat
or steal or tolerate those who do as a
police officer in the town of Hingham
what would your code of conduct be it
would absolutely be very strict I'm not
somebody who has ever compromised my own
morals I always stick by them in high
school or college if it came to you know
underage drinking or whatever that case
may be I had opportunities I stuck with
what I felt was right and I would do the
same as a police officer without
question thank you good questions um -
two questions for you mr. Carr first you
know someone who's grown up in this town
and you know you've had professional
experience in different places but as
you think about the police department
right now and hang them what sort of
challenges or issues are we facing as a
community that's a really good question
I'm not sure I have a great answer for
that one
superfish you think about some of the
issues at the police officers face and
what might make a police job challenging
what what sorts of things come to mind
cuz I think you know when when you were
growing up and hang them you know if
we've been here 17 years and if it feels
like it's changed and you've experienced
Hingham you know as a child so as as you
think about being a police officer what
I do actually have an answer for that
one now that I think about that I think
it's just it's a much more public image
the police officers have
and you know with social media and
everybody pulling out their phones at
every instant I think officers do you
have to hold themselves to a higher
standard and really rely on those morals
in order to you know maintain that
maintain being a trustworthy figure in
the town and someone people can rely on
rather than seeing as somebody who's
just out to get them which also then
goes back to community policing and
being a part in being present and just
being involved but I think making sure
that you're not that you stay in line
you stick to your morals you stick to
your code in an era where deaf people
are not hesitant to pull out their phone
and wait for you to do something wrong
thank you and my final question is
obviously from your work experience
you're someone who takes on a challenge
you work pretty hard at it you know how
would what aspirations would you have on
you know coming into the police
department in terms of your development
as a member of our law enforcement team
my goal would just be to be as
productive as a member of the force as
possible however that leads me in a
career path is is however that turns out
but certainly always striving to be a
better police officer take advantage of
training opportunities and just never
stop learning thank you and just before
we before we conclude do you have any
questions for us or is there anything in
you know the course of our conversation
that that you wanted to mention no I'm
just very grateful for the opportunity
to be here tonight and want to thank you
very much well we appreciate it as well
so we thank you and next week the board
will be making making decisions so again
we appreciate your coming in this
evening thank you very much thank you
and our final candidate this evening is
mr. John Thomas
mr. Thomas welcome Mary power oh thank
you so much that's that's fine thank you
if you'd like to sit right over there
thank you mr. Thomas what we'd like to
do we'll take about 10 or 15 minutes
we'll start by asking you to just please
introduce yourself to the board tell us
a little bit about about you about your
experience about why you're interested
in becoming a police officer for the
town of Hingham then we'll each take
turns asking one or two questions and at
the conclusion if you have any questions
for us or anything else that you'd like
to add so if I may please could you just
tell us a little about yourself and why
you'd like to be a Hingham police
officer for those who don't know me I'm
John Thomas and I'm born and raised here
in Hingham and I went through hanging
public schools graduated from Hingham
high school after that I did a year of
college at Dean College and Franklin
Mass I then immediately started working
for my father's company right in town
and that's when I started working
closely with hangul Police Department
and I have family and family friends in
the police community so it's kind of why
I'm into it thank you
Paul would you like to start sure yeah
can I call you John yeah sure
hey I've known your father for a number
of years
tell me something John what do you think
your experience working with the police
it is done in terms of insights into the
police world of the police mission I'm
talking about here and hang him
obviously yeah
I think that brought me to a lot of
situations where you have to work quick
and you see a lot of things that a lot
of people don't see and it just makes
you a well-rounded hardworking person I
think and yeah what do you think about
the the concept of living in the
community that you police I think it's
wonderful to be able to if I did get the
job to be able to give back to your
community that has made you into the
person you are in in terms of the
qualities of a good police officer
whether it's here and Hingham or
anywhere where someone puts on a uniform
with a badge and a gun what are the
three non-negotiable qualities that
somebody who's a police officer in your
opinion has to have my opinion I would
say compassion integrity and leadership
with truthfulness and all of that but
with truthfulness and all of that is
that integrity afternoon Tegrity okay
thank you just a couple things I noticed
and thank you for this resume because it
contains I think some additional
information I wonder if you could just
tell us a little bit about the work that
you did at the Cardinal Cushing School
in Hanover so I worked with the
handicapped and the special-needs there
for community service for high school
and I worked closely with the older
group and you got to see a lot of things
you don't see and work with people that
you don't work with the whole time
and it was good to work with people that
are unfortunate and and just you know as
you think about some of the experiences
that you had there and you think about
becoming a Hingham police officer are
there you know are there things that you
gained from doing that that you think
might help you be an effective police
officer yeah I definitely don't take
everything for granted and you also
don't know people are going through a
struggling with and if you know in your
experience so you know one of the things
that strikes me as as I've had the
opportunity to interact with the police
officers I get a really good
appreciation for the fact that a police
officer has to make a very quick
assessment of a situation and a very
quick decision and in a lot of cases you
don't have the time or the opportunity
to ask somebody what to do or to run it
by somebody which I've really come to
understand and appreciate is is pretty
challenging but in in your work
experience you you know you experience
that to some degree as well I just
wondered if there was you know an
experience or something in you know your
your professional background where you
know you had to make a quick decision or
a quick assessment on your own
that might just kind of give us a little
bit of a preview as to what you might do
if you if you had that circumstance
happen as a police officer that does a
story come to mind or an experience well
every day every day I deal with car
accidents and all sorts of types of
accidents and you have to be quick with
your thought and you have to be able to
plan well and you have to be efficient
it's really it yeah thank you very much
Karen yeah I guess following up on
Mary's question you know that one of the
things I guess I saw when I did I
noticed in your resume you did the
citizens police academy
I participated in that a fall or two ago
and one of the things that struck me
particularly about the sort of accident
scene demonstration was the precise
teamwork and as a as a tow truck
operator you're coming on that scene too
and you're part of that team so it's
this combination Mary is very sort of
mentioning of being able to make a quick
assessment and quick individual
decisions but also be part of a team on
a scene and I guess I'm wondering how
how you see some of the qualities you
have the experiences you have what would
make you a good team player for the hema
Police Department yeah whether it's
working with the police or working with
other tow drivers that I work with you
have to be able to work through and plan
quickly and effectively on how you're
gonna get the job done and get it clear
so that the roadway is clean yep
and then I noticed that you've got a
number of specialized trainings that I
think are very relevant and wonder if
you could maybe talk a little bit about
your EMT training your firearms training
the time you've taken to educate
yourself and you know to me put yourself
on a stronger track to be a police
officer so I did an EMT course in 2013
and 14 and it was like four months and I
got through the whole entire course and
you learned a lot and I'm fortunately
didn't pass the national exam but I'd
learned a lot from it and yeah and then
my firearms course it's a lot of gun
safety and even then yeah I still
practice gun safety going to the gun
range and all that and so it's good
that's great thank you did you have any
questions for us or is there anything
else that you'd want to make sure that
we were aware of I don't have any
questions I just want to thank you for
this time and this opportunity I'm
grateful for it we are grateful to you
know is I think an important part of
community policing
is having the opportunity to have people
who have grown up in this community and
who know this community step forward and
I think when we have candidates such as
yourself who have been in Hingham it
really just helps helps the police
department with its mission so we know
that there are a lot of different
options that are out there and we're
very grateful that you're considering
coming to work for the town so we thank
you so much and we'll be making our
decision next week thank you thank you
so there will be some additional work
being completed by the police department
we will take this matter up again next
week and how nice to see that we have
three local people coming forward to
candidates gee it's really nice to see
so we have a forecast update that's
scheduled to begin at 8 o'clock when the
advisory committee is going to join us
so what I'm actually going to do is to
take up our possible votes I believe we
might have an appointment selectmen Town
Administrator reports so our first vote
is Lincoln Day and Lincoln Day this year
in the town of Hingham will be on
Saturday February 10th there will be a
ceremony at the old ship Church at 11
o'clock and then we will process to the
Lincoln statue and it is customary for
this board to sign a proclamation and
while it's long I seem to remember that
you've read this in years past terrific
what is so inclined all right
ladies and gentlemen citizens of Hingham
this is the town of Hingham
Massachusetts proclamation whereas the
town of Hingham was settled in 1635 by a
small band of Puritan pilgrims many of
whom came from Hingham England and
environs and whereas among the
descendants of those original settlers
were two famous American public figures
who shared the common family name
Lincoln as well as a common heritage and
whereas it is a long-standing hanging
tradition to honor and celebrate their
birthdays general Benjamin Lincoln a
lifelong Hingham citizen and hero of the
American Revolution in Abraham Lincoln
our 16th president and the towering
figure of the Civil War and whereas we
honor and celebrate the lives and deeds
of the two lincoln's because of the
indelible legacy of community building
and preservation they have left for us
and whereas in this year 2018 we pay
special honor to four centuries of our
citizens those famous like Benjamin
Lincoln and Abraham Lincoln and those
unknown to history who worked in a
myriad of ways to build and sustain this
wonderful community of Hingham and the
broader communities of state and nation
and whereas the preservation of
community is a perpetual task in which
each generation must fully participate
now therefore we the Board of Selectmen
of the town of Hingham do hereby
officially proclaim Saturday February
10th 2018 Lincoln Day we urge also that
as many citizens as possible join us at
the old ship church on Saturday February
10th 2018 at 11 a.m. for a patriotic
ceremony of celebration
finally we urge each citizen to take to
heart the examples of the two Lincoln's
and those are four centuries of Hingham
citizens and we urge each citizen to
participate in some concrete way in the
strengthening and preservation of this
community of Hingham and the broader
communities of state and nations for the
generations which will succeed us
given under our hands and sealove
Hingham this 30th day of January 2018
Mary power Chairman Paul K Healey Karen
a Johnson I've got a tough act to follow
next Saturday when I read this at the
old ship I would like I would like to
make a motion to proclaim February 10th
2018 as Lincoln Day in the town of
Hingham second all those in favor aye
okay we have two votes we have a vote
for a license sure why don't we do the
appointment I'd like to move that we
appoint Jacqueline Zane to the
Conservation Commission to fill an
unexpired term ending June 30 2019 all
those in favor aye
I'd like to congratulate thank miss Zane
congratulate her and say that we are
looking forward for your beginning to
serve the town we have a license one-day
wine and malt beverages licensed to
Diane to Napoli on behalf of special
needs athletic partnership for the snap
st. Patrick's Day party to be held at
the kingdom community center on Saturday
March 9th 2018 from 6 p.m. to 11 p.m.
she's not here but my understanding is
he has approved this yes second all
those in favor aye
okay and then lastly we Tom walked us
through the town of Hingham Street
acceptance policy at our libel Eve that
was at our last meeting and we as we do
with a lot of these we decided to hold
off I don't believe there was any
feedback from from the community and I
believe that attorney Murphy received
confirmation from staff that everybody
was comfortable with it Tom yes it's
been supposed circulated everyone was
calm
well with it and receive nothing I
talked to Tom separately and Susan
Murphy as well okay we good to go on
this move to approve the town of Hingham
Street acceptance policy for insertion
and Board of Selectmen policies and
procedures manual second any further
discussion all those in favor aye
okay so let's why don't we do selectmen
and Town Administrator reports
Tom do you not want to vote article C
until later you want to wait on that I
think I'm just gonna wait only don't
forget it yep yeah only because that's
posted at 9:15 so if people can help
remind me so we don't we don't miss that
Tom Town Administrator report so within
the good news category we have a couple
of grants to announce from this week the
Hingham and Central Ford's of Health
working together have received an
18-month grant for $25,000 from the Blue
Hill Community Health Alliance this will
address the hoarding disorder associated
clutter and the related stigma through
public health education and clinician
led online treatment groups the data
will be collected by the BU School of
Social Work and be published in a
peer-reviewed journal article we've also
received an engineering grant through
the town of Inghams engineering
department acting through the Board of
Selectmen we've received a $50,000
planning assistance grant from the
Executive Office of Energy and
Environmental Affairs the grant will
augment offset the town's cost for the
ongoing efforts associated with
designing engineering and permitting
resiliency improvements to strengthen
the coastal infrastructure with in
Hingham Inner Harbor and if anyone was
down to harbor this morning with that
tide you'll see why this is a timely
timely grant to receive we had some
minor coastal flooding down there this
morning and finally I just wanted to
thank everyone over at the Hingham DPW
for their efforts to clear today's storm
this was a tricky storm it came in a
little bit late around 6 a.m. a little
bit earlier right at the beginning of
the of the in the morning commute it was
a heavier than anticipated storm a lot
of high winds
drifting and you know we got 110 miles
of roadway and 60 miles of sidewalk
these folks have to do have to clear and
when you're out treating them and all of
a sudden you get a heavier than normal
storm you got to go switch all your
equipment to plows from treatment from
treatment equipment it's um it's a it's
a heavy lift and they did a great job
today I thought yeah and I feel like
then they switch back to treatment at
the end you know when it started to get
cold this afternoon the salt trucks were
back out there and I would just just add
to that that our preparation for the
storm this morning actually began about
2:30 this morning which is when all of
the crews were out sanding and salting
the road in anticipation of the snow and
waiting for it so that's you know that's
that's a that's a very long effort and I
suspect that there are some people who
have not been home for close to 24 hours
because as Tom said we have a hundred
and ten miles of roadway and 60 miles of
sidewalk thank you anything else time
that's it's going to be done at the okay
I'm going to go to Karen sure okay so a
couple things on the sort of work side
I'm continuing really to concentrate my
efforts on some veterans issues with
Keith German and father bills as well as
some affordable housing issues with the
affordable housing trust the housing and
the housing authority and again with
with father bills so that's sort of the
bulk of my office time I'd like to give
a couple a couple of shoutouts one is to
Lily fartin and Team USA the u18 hockey
team who won gold medal in Russia about
I don't know a couple weeks ago really
really fantastic effort was fun too fun
to keep up with that news and then on
the veterans front I'd like to say that
both the wrestling team and the girls
basketball team this week will be
honoring our veterans at their matches
and basketball games respectively
wrestling is tomorrow evening I think
around 6:30 and the girls basketball
game is this Friday evening at 6:30 and
you know
you've talked about the the veterans
appreciation Club at the high school you
know the fact that these sports teams
are taking special time to to recognize
the outstanding contributions of our
veterans I just think it's um is
admirable so if you can get out and
support our teams and our veterans
that'd be terrific
I'm gonna give you a couple a couple
more minutes I'll do mine and then no
pressure no pressure I wanted to just
mention that first of all the mass
Municipal Association the MMA had its
annual meeting a couple Fridays ago Tom
attended I attended Jamie Grylls in the
audience for something that's coming up
along with Emily Wentworth and this is a
day-long conference with colleagues we
heard the governor speak we had a chance
to attend workshops I attended a
workshop actually on public safety with
the Chelsea police chief that was just
fascinating I attended a legal update so
that I could keep up with my to my two
colleagues it was just a really nice
opportunity I also attended a a women's
elected official breakfast and it was
really nice to see the number of women
who are in leadership positions in the
Commonwealth so it was really a great
day a chance to share best practices
Network there's a trade show component
where a number of Hingham partners were
there and it's nice to catch up with
them and that's setting as well I don't
know if you had anything to add about
the MMA yeah it was the same for me I
you know I always loved the trade show
in there you get to see the breadth of
services and an equipment that's used to
keep me his pal he's running across the
state and I got to I got to attend some
some wonderful budgeting seminars as
well as social media use these are all
burgeoning topics that are that are
important to stay on top of so and I
would also say that in in looking at
some of that for example I was at this
one about the police force and as they
were sharing a lot of best practices and
different things I found myself with
many of them saying yep we do that yep
we do that and it actually was very you
know not just a chance to learn some new
things but it
just reinforced to me that how well-run
Hingham is which is a great credit to to
our teams last Saturday the you know
we're in the middle of budget we're
gonna do a forecast update in a minute I
attended the school budget discussion
with the Advisory subcommittee and the
School Committee we spent about three
hours on a Saturday morning talking
about the school budget which I'm
grateful for everybody's time I would
mention to the public that tomorrow
evening beginning at seven o'clock at
the hang of middle school is a Hingham
Education Forum that is being sponsored
by the 6p tos across the Hingham public
school and this is an opportunity to ask
questions and have dialogue about many
things our appreciation to members of
the school committee and members of the
school administration and principles for
making themself available for what is
going to prove to be I think a very a
very informative evening before I turn
it over to mr. Healy I'd also mention on
a on a more somber note that within the
last three weeks
Hingham has lost three citizens who have
contributed to our community in many
ways through working for the town
through volunteering for the town and we
regrettably lost Tom studly and John
Stoddard and Willis Earthman and on
behalf of the board in town we offer our
condolences to their families and our
gratitude for the many many
contributions that each of them made to
just make this community a better place
so Paul anything else you know no no I
think I'm good just because I'm not
talking doesn't mean I'm not busy I've
said that before I'll say it again we
all work in our respective roles of
Selectmen addressing you know enquiries
that the town makes and serving its
needs you know I was outside Saturday as
I'm sure many of you were enjoying the
weather and one of my neighbors came
over and he
started providing me with his opinion of
an issue in town and he stopped himself
and said gee I I really apologize you're
on your day off and I said as a
selectman I'm never off so go ahead and
keep talking and that's how it is you
know if people have a beef or problem
you know you pick up the phone my
numbers in the book so that's all I
really want to say make sure you call
Paul so it's a it's 8 o'clock and the
Advisory Committee has joined us and we
welcome them before we get into the
joint session on Community Preservation
we're going to do a forecast update and
you know just for the audience one it
one of the things around this time of
year where we're working the advisory
committees working on settling the town
budget and in an effort to try to share
a little bit more information but also
recognizing that people are watching
from home and sometimes the the page of
very small print really doesn't show up
very well on the TV screen so what we've
tried to do and we've got it up on the
screen is to just put together a little
bit of an overview presentation members
of the advisory committee have copies of
our very detailed forecast document we
also have additional copies at the table
so anyone is more than welcome but tom
is just going to kind of walk through a
little bit of where we are and then I'm
gonna touch on one thing at the end so
let's turn it over to you Tom thank you
very much Mary okay so again in an
effort to try to simplify the forecast
which can be complicated we we tried to
break it down into a more understandable
flow so the financial forecast for
Hingham is generally split into two
categories one revenue and the other
expenses and the so the revenue outlook
in town and we
have a comparison for the projected FY
19 versus the the anticipated than FY 18
so the tax levy and FY 18 was
approximately eighty million dollars
with the projected 19 tax levy of eighty
two point three million dollars other
revenue from eighteen was twenty seven
point four and in nineteen we're
anticipating other revenue dropping to
twenty seven point two for total
forecast at revenues in eighteen of 107
point four that's one hundred and seven
million four hundred thousand dollars
and in for FY nineteen projection of a
hundred nine million five hundred
thousand dollars so expenses and it's in
it's important to understand that we're
still early in the process where these
budgets are still being reviewed so
these are the early expenses and this
includes a simple two percent increase
over the prior year for the school
budget and obviously that will that will
change to some extent as we go through
the budgeting process but for now in
these numbers you're looking at a simple
two percent increase so in articles four
five and six you're looking at an FY 18
number of one hundred and three point
five million with the projection for FY
nineteen of 100 points 106.5 capital
outlay of 2.2 and eighteen to two point
three and nineteen and with a total of
mother categories equaling one point
four million in expenses in eighteen and
one point five and nineteen and that
brings our totals to about a hundred and
seven point three million in expenses
for eighteen with the projection of 110
point three in nineteen so in eighteen
we saw a slight surplus at the end of
the process of just about a hundred
thousand dollars and in nineteen as of
today we're budgeting of we're looking
at about an eight hundred thousand
dollar deficit however that will change
and I'll go into that here in a minute
so how next page we recap some of the
revenue numbers and we summer summarize
that so you're looking at
approximately in revenue you're looking
at approximately a 2.1 percent increase
I'm sorry a 2.1 million dollar or two
percent increase over a prior-year
anticipated in revenue so updates since
the first forecast was presented back in
November we're looking at a decrease in
our new growth projections of about
three hundred twenty five thousand
dollars that's largely due to some of
the larger projects in town not being
built on the timeline we were
anticipating earlier in the year and
that includes some of the ones down and
shipped down the shipyard the Avalon
Brio and a Linden ponds building etc so
state aid
we got the meri and I were at the MMA in
Boston last week and we heard the
governor's budget presentation and he's
looking at approximately for the town of
Hingham of about one hundred eighty
eight thousand dollar increase in state
aid this year now again that's the
governor's budget subject to change as
it goes through their process and then
local receipts we're looking at
approximately two hundred and eighty
thousand dollar increase over last year
motor vehicle exit to break that down
you're looking at about a hundred and
fifty thousand dollar in anticipated
increase in motor vehicle excise tax the
meals tax of a increase of about eighty
thousand dollars and twenty five
thousand dollars in each and licenses
fees and permits and ambulance fees so
the potential updates to the FY nineteen
budget the as I said as I just stated
the state aid number is a projected
number right now that's just the
governor's budget still has to go
through the entire state review process
so that's subject to change the local
receipts the FY 19 local receipt
forecast it's important to note that
we're looking at about nine just under
not 95 so ninety four point eight
percent of the FY 17 actuals which was
the last actual as the town has realized
you know ninety-five percent is kind of
our threshold we don't like to to
project a whole lot higher than that
gets it gets iffy and as we learned in
2008 across the state higher projections
can be dangerous
okay our next slide is a simple pie
chart trying to explain how revenue
canoe components where they come from so
if you're looking at the largest piece
of the pie the 70% of all revenue curve
all the revenue coming in is coming from
the tax levy
approximately 10% from state aid
approximately 8% from local receipts 5%
is the country-club in the sewer it's
important to real to remember that those
are offset by their by their enterprise
fund and then 4% from the excluded debt
and 2% through other categories
including new growth it's very important
at this time to note that we do not
expect additional significant revenue
change there right the large revenue
changes just occurred right so between
November and this forecast those are the
largest revenue changes we're going to
see okay so expenses this is the other
side of the forecast now these haven't
been as flushed out yet we're still in
the middle of the process the school
department will be coming in next week
for a joint meeting with the board and
addcom here in this room next Tuesday so
we'll probably get some new some new
information at that meeting but for now
again to recap we're looking at expenses
of one hundred and seven point three
million and eighteen to one hundred and
ten point three million in 19 or a three
million dollar change equaling
approximately 2.8 percent increase and
again that is with a school budget
increase estimated at 2 percent and we
know that that will be higher so what so
what does that mean so the update since
the last forecast they haven't been any
expense updates which is why we're
looking at the same numbers the
potential updates and this is really
where a lot of people are probably
thinking yes this is likely to change
the group insurance we don't know we
haven't received that number yet from
the GIC so the town joined the GIC which
is a state health plan provider last
year we haven't received their
anticipated change over last year yet
for this coming year we hope to receive
that in
in late January so that number will
change as a as a potential expense the
education budget we've seen some
presentations publicly both on the
school committee and others where
they're projecting about in the ink an
additional increase over what we what we
are proposing in here of an another of
another two million dollars to bring
their total increase to approximately
six point one percent over over last
year again that's not in here yet simply
because it hasn't gone all the way
through that process
capital outlay recommendation we haven't
received that yet they're coming in in a
couple of weeks and they'll we'll go
through their process as well then the
town budget recommendations right now
the administration proposed budget does
include a two hundred sixty four
thousand dollars in additional requests
beyond my message of a level service
budget in that equalled approximately a
three point nine percent total increase
okay what are the next steps so on next
Tuesday February 6th we'll be holding
the selectmen will be holding a joint
school a joint meeting with the School
Committee and advisory to flush out the
school the school's budget that
presentation and discussion will occur
again next Tuesday in this room in
mid-february we hope to hear from
capital outlay and in late February
early March in that timeframe we haven't
got the dates yet the all three of us
the selectmen the school committee and
advisory will be voting the budgets okay
yep so do you follow Karen any questions
for Tom or any comments yeah I mean it
may be a little granular at this stage
of the game but Minh maybe you and I
could can chat and we can bring it back
next time but I'm I'm wondering about
the carrying of the meals tax within the
local receipts line item is that where
it's all baked in there so there's no
separate meals tax Stabilization Fund
like the meals tax reserve that we carry
through FY 19 so that the meals tax the
meals tax reserve that is going through
19 was the first we we accumulated about
two million dollars in the meals Tax
Fund before we moved them into local
receipts and the idea was to give that
back over about five years to just sort
of smooth it out so next year will be
the last year of that okay the other
meals tax are in the local receipts
number of nine point nine million the
detail is that back on I think it's page
four and the meals tax amount right now
Tom it's 800 right yes eight hundred
thousand dollars okay and I'm sorry Tom
you said those those numbers are being
carried at 94% of actuals yes not a
ninety four point eight that's the
overall the actual yeah so the meals tax
numbers specifically Karen was at ninety
nine point three of the seventeen
actuals okay
but overall so overall in the aggregate
local receipts are being carried at
about just under not 95% of actuals
right is that you're saying yeah yeah
yeah
okay I mean you know so just so
everybody knows right the forecast group
meets but because we have three
selectmen we can only have one selectmen
in the forecast room so I said to Tom
just the other day I was I was glad that
this was you know coming up at this time
because you know we sort of operate
outside outside this level of detail so
you know I appreciate the presentation
tonight and you know I am gonna spend
some time with it and will likely have a
question or two I'm only see if we I
know yes I mean if if you look at it if
you were to roll in all the numbers that
we have right now we have a 2.8 million
dollar deficit right now which is I
think a little larger than we've had in
past years at this time we've had them
over - but it it at least for me it
feels like it's within reach it's more
challenging this year I think we've been
talking for three or four years that
revenue growth was going to slow down
and I think we're seeing that
materialize and so we are gonna we're
gonna have our work cut out for us
and you know as you look at the
components of revenue as Tom said you
know with the local receipts and the new
growth if we are too aggressive in
forecasting those amounts there's no
other place to make up that revenue we
would have to dip into our fund balance
our rainy day fund and that got us into
some trouble ten years ago so we don't
want to do that right and that's why as
we're looking for example in our local
receipts we don't want to be overly
aggressive two years ago as an example
ambulance fees kind of dropped off
unexpectedly to the tune of a couple of
hundred thousand dollars because of some
changes in I think it was Medicaid so
you know I would just affirm with this
board we back in I think it was October
in November we talked about the fact
that
when we had the forecast review back in
November we said this was the revenue
that was on the table that we didn't
envision any sort of an override we
didn't envision applying any of the
unused levy capacity because that was
offsetting the cost of the middle school
I guess I'm just kind of looking to my
colleagues I I haven't changed my mind
on that ya know I have you know I think
that's the message everybody got frankly
in November was that this is the pie
that we had to work with and you know no
I no appetite for that and just just to
sort of dimensionalize that a little bit
at this I mentioned that I was at the
Saturday advisory meeting with with the
school committee and there was some
conversation about you know how Hingham
kind of compares to other communities
and we know we like to do a lot of
benchmarking in this town we're we're
good at that it's one of the reasons
we're a triple-a and what we do is we
take 20 communities and and the
Personnel Board identified these
communities many years ago and and some
of them are geographically close to
hanging them some of them are comparable
in size and demographics to hang them
some of them perhaps a little bit
different in terms of demographics so we
have some communities like the W
communities Wellesley and Weston that
perhaps are a little more affluent than
Hingham we have other communities that
are nearby and you know there was some
talk about well you know how do we
compare and you know does that mean that
that you know we have some opportunity
with revenue and I mentioned some
numbers off the cuff that had been done
about six or seven years ago and went
back after an update and I just want to
share this with with my colleagues and
with the audience for a second because I
think it paints the picture for why this
board is saying that the revenue we have
is the revenue we have so if you look at
Hingham up at the very top if you look
at our 2017 residential tax bill it's
$11 and 77 cents
every thousand dollars of assessed value
so that's how our tax bills are
calculated and you know what if you go
and you compare that to the twenty towns
that are listed on the bottom of the
screen we are number 18 out of 20 ours
is one of the lowest and you know I
would like to I would like to think that
that's part of what attracts people to
hang them the property values can be
high but relative to some other
communities we have a fairly low tax
rate but I think just looking at that
tax rate by itself doesn't really tell
you a lot about Hingham so let me take
it a step further
our average single-family property tax
bill in FY eighteen is nine thousand
four hundred eighty nine dollars where
we're ranked number 11 out of 20 so
while our tax rate is lower compared to
some of our peer communities because of
the value of our properties the tax bill
checks that we all right is a little bit
higher comparing the median household
income for all those communities
kingdoms median household income is a
hundred six thousand eight hundred and
fifty four dollars which ranks us twelve
out of those twenty benchmark
communities and then the last piece I
just say is so so let's just think about
putting ourselves you know we're all
taxpayers so what that means is if we
take our average property tax bill
against our household income for for
somebody in Hingham your property tax
bill is about just under nine percent of
your total budget your household budget
and what was noteworthy to me is that
when I compared that to the other
nineteen benchmark communities we are
ranked number six and so what that says
to me is that as we're thinking about
our revenue picture and we're thinking
about the citizens in this community we
need to understand against a backdrop of
all of this that for many households in
Hingham the existing property tax bill
is a big burden it is a bigger burden to
a household budget that it may be in
other communities so while our tax rate
might be one of the lowest
we need to keep in mind the Czech people
are paying and the proportion of their
income and understand that in this
community with many seniors and with
many young families the median household
income we have I think we have a little
bit more economic diversity than some of
our other communities and there a couple
other things we need to think about we
need to keep in mind the new tax law
remember that for exemption the property
tax exemption the combination of
property tax and state tax it's a ten
thousand dollar limit our average tax
bills just about ten thousand so you
know I think some people probably a lot
of people on the Advisory Committee you
already know what the impact of of the
tax bill is on you know of the tax law
and your on your tax bill but I think
what we may find is that there are
people who could be adversely affected
by that I think we also have to keep in
mind again as I said the percentage of
household income and the third thing I
think we all have to remember too is
that we have a lot of capital projects
very worthy capital projects that we've
talked about before we've talked about
the wharfs we've talked about a school
we've talked about Town Hall the library
fire stations you know country potential
numbers 50 to 80 million dollars and
when the Advisory when when the Advisory
Committee was with us a few months ago
they talked about the fact that within
our budget we've got we've got room in
the next five years for about sixteen
million dollars of projects so what that
says to me is that if those large
capital projects move forward we might
be in a position where we have to ask
the taxpayers if if they would be
willing to pay for those things what
that's just to me all the more important
is that we have to live within our means
with the revenue that we have we have to
keep the taxpayers in mind we have to
understand you know just keep some of
this stuff in mind and
so as as we're moving forward and and
we're looking well I think we may have a
little bit of a challenge with the
budget what that information says to me
is that is that we we have a
responsibility to keep all this in mind
as we move forward with with what may be
some difficult decisions I think it's a
really helpful slide Mary and I
appreciate you and Tom taking the time
to pull it together I think they're
they're very useful metrics I think
they're it gives you a visual of I think
the feeling that we all have but it
gives you a visual and and some data to
analyze it again so I appreciate both
you and Tom taking the time to pull that
together as I said before when people
speak to me from this town that that's
the one consistent message that I get
uniformly across the board I I said at
the school committee meeting that at the
dilemma for a lot of us in this room and
our advisory colleagues people in town
would like great services really nice
stuff and low taxes and those three
things aren't necessarily all compatible
so the job we have with our school
committee partners as well is to figure
out how do we strike that balance as we
move forward and we have always done
that in a collaborative way and we look
forward to doing that again anything
else on this okay so next on the agenda
so many of you weren't here when Paul
Healy so eloquently read the
proclamation for Lincoln Day but there
was one line that I thought it was a
really good introduction to our next
topic in our proclamation we talked
about the preservation of community is a
perpetual task in which each generation
must fully participate and that's what
we're really about to do right now with
the community preservation and so I'd
like to invite Carole piles and
yeah you see we thought maybe if you
wanted to come up to the tables so as
we're going through projects and Jim
welcome you know we thought if you're
probably more comfortable sitting giving
you the prison's presentation yep and
you know if if I could just ask before
before we started and Carol maybe will
will will ask you first but you have
members of your team at the table you
have members of your team in the
audience I just asked you to introduce
the members of your committee and your
team and then Lucy if you could please
introduce the members of the advisory
committee that are here this evening
these groups of people have been working
pretty long hours pretty hard to do
great work and I think it's important
that that the community knows who's
who's behind all the great work we're
going to see
well behind us yes sure hi good evening
I'm Carol piles chairman of Community
Preservation Committee to my right is my
vice chairman Jim Conroy and Carol
Costello who makes us all look good and
it's Roger coming tonight do we now and
Roger and other members of our committee
who are here tonight our Dan white and
Jim Watson and Larry Lindner and Bill
Harrington and then the others and the
committee who are not here we Sarah
Khouri and Bob Mosher and Vicki Donlon
okay we're delighted to present such
good projects to you this even this is
really a challenge because these cheers
just before you start to see to
introduce the members of the Advisory
right has done a small wit vice-chair in
the front row over here we have Bob
Curley Erin Kelly Kevin Sheehan the next
row Julie straily George dannis Dave
Anderson Nicole straily Viktor Bout Tara
next row Libby Claypool I'm looking Dan
Coughlin is there anybody between you
know okay and Tom's
Thom belly a and I think we're missing
one person
two people I don't see the other two yet
did they get here no okay did I miss
anyone okay thank you okay
Thank You Lucy so you will be changing
the slides as we go along Carol the
first thing we want to talk about
tonight is that CPA has been around
since 2000 and we joined early on we
were one of the early towns and so since
2003 we have been able to devote to
twenty-two million two hundred and
eleven thousand dollars back to our town
in terms of historic preservation open
space community housing and then in 2013
recreation was also added so those
projects have come in and you can see on
that first page the percentage and we
still have the same challenge we had
last year when we presented to you and
that is we desperately are trying to get
community housings share of the pot a
little higher and we were maybe able to
do that a little bit more this year
okay the next page is just some random
pictures of some of the projects that
we'll be presenting to you tonight
we call it bills and pools but you can
as you can see from the picture the next
page is CPC recommendations to the town
meeting for 2018 and we'll go through
each one of these individuals but they
are our administrative fund Hingham
affordable housing trust Opportunity
Fund conservation of historic town
documents p.m. cemetery erosion control
memorial bell tower mechanism repair the
old fort house as the Richardson house
archeology and installation Harper
walkway extension the whole street field
play area and the South Shore Country
Club pool design and construction design
and in our numbers you will note as we
go through that our debt service
payments are also included we're paying
off the Heritage Museum at 165 thousand
plus per year and the Lehner property at
315 thousand per year those debt service
payments count in the category of the
projects yes okay yes they do sorry for
the interruption
okay the next page we have the community
Preservation Committee revenue and
luckily it adds up to the same number as
we had on the last page and of course
this comes with a 1.5 percent surcharge
on your property taxes and so that first
number a million eleven thousand five
ninety four is this year's collection
the state contribution for this year is
a hundred and seventy four thousand and
we have accumulated in reserve and
clawed back from unfinished projects
388,000 so that all goes into us having
a million five seventy three and change
to spend this year and if you break it
into categories which is always a very
interesting look you realize that our
Community Housing has gone way up this
year we were able to truly fund them at
a level that made us very happy
historic open space and Recreation which
adds up to the same number okay so the
first is our own community of
preservation committee administrative
fund and is fifty thousand dollars this
year this account enables the CPC to
operate quite literally we couldn't do
it without them the CPC act allows a
total of five percent of the town's
annual CPA budget to be used for
administrative fund this request and
there's a typo here in the next line
this request is a total of four point
two percent not two point four percent
of available funds for this year that 1
million 185 this is a rolling fund that
does not coincide with the fiscal year
these funds are available at any time
for unexpected legal fees costs
associated with cpa projects and with
one question we always get is why the
legal fees so high especially since we
have three lawyers on the committee this
year but that doesn't affect us that's
used for
the town councillor Service land deed
registrations closing costs conservation
restrictions surveying and land
acquisition expenses okay
the Hingham affordable housing trust we
were able to put together four hundred
and sixty four thousand five hundred
dollars for them this year the proponent
is the Hingham affordable housing trust
the scope is funds are set aside in the
hht opportunity fund to assist with
creation and preservation of affordable
housing in Hingham you all know what
that is any questions yes so for the
Opportunity Fund I know with some of
your other projects you talked about you
talked about a clawback with the
Opportunity Fund is there some presumed
length of time that that housing trust
would need is not necessarily although
this year because we had given them
money in the past for a project on Beale
Street which I think you all and and
others have said please hold up on that
so that put it in a lockbox for them and
it was a big chunk of money so with
discussion with them and a vote we
decided to take that back and re gift it
this year so it goes into their
Opportunity Fund which they can use for
anything if it had stayed where it was
it was only for that particular project
and they couldn't have used it for
anything else so that helped us get
their number up higher they'll sure and
so what's the net grant aside from the
clawback funds then what's the new money
this year
well there's 10% which is 180 18,000 I
don't have the numbers right in front of
me but they're clawback and that adds up
to 464 plus is a hundred and six
thousand and new money I think you know
I'm sorry I don't have the exact
breakdown it's a combination of new plus
reuse of their old money plus the
natural 10% that they have to get Oh
okay and and the the sort of that
clawback circle allows them greater
flexibility in the use of the originally
granted funds they can use it for
anything and if the Beale Street
property comes back online again they
can use it for that too great thank you
you can't have Jim's gonna give us the
next presentation okay so this is a
phase two of a three phase project
possibly a four phase project to
conserve and fortify the ancient town
records that we have in the clerk's
office which date back to the middle of
the seventeenth century last year ten
bound volumes were restored conserved
this year we recommend three thousand
and fifty dollars to fund the projected
cost of restoring another dozen of those
volumes and you can see from the slide
and the handout that they are ancient
and fragile and subject to loss if
they're not conserved and cared for so
the conservation is done by a
professional who repairs rips and
bindings and fortifies week pages and
such came on came in under his estimated
cost last year and we're hopeful of if
not doing that at least not exceeding
two three thousand this year and next
year after that the hope is to if not
deal with the remaining 50 volumes have
not yet been dealt with which are a
little later then at least maybe half of
those and then finish it up the year
after that so is there any plan to
digitize any of these records there is
talk about it but there is no specific
plan as yet it's quite costly to do that
but that is the hope and the longer-term
goal okay
storage at the town clerk's office so
once the volumes have been repaired
stabilized and fully conserved are there
any any sort of special care that the
clerk needs to take or we should be
taking in order to preserve the volumes
once they've been conserved I'm not
aware of any special hermetically sealed
chambers or anything but there is talk
and discussion about a longer range hope
to to store and conserve all the town
and possibly the Historical Society
documents in one place but for the
moment the conservator is confident that
the conditions in the town clerk's
office are suitable yes okay thank you
they are being stored in acid free boxes
yep it sounds better than like acid
start the next one cemetery ham cemetery
erosion control if you will look at your
probably all record recognize the place
we're talking about it's the corner a
corner of the cemetery adjacent to the
old ship Church it's been described to
us as sort of a confluence of three
historic assets the cemetery itself the
old ship church on the bell tower which
all come together at that point and the
immediate concern is the erosion of that
slope that you see on the slide some of
those hilltop graves will end up in that
driveway if they are not contained and
controlled pretty promptly and many of
them are 17th century graves and the
cemetery board looked at a number of
alternatives to try to stop that erosion
control but so that's their first
priority of a multi-year plan for the
cemetery but that one's the urgent need
because of that continued erosion and
they considered a stone wall
retain that space but figured out in
their own calculations that that would
be prohibitively expensive and also I've
heard that there could be a kind of an
echo chamber effect from those bells
bouncing off a stone wall
so they've opted for a shrubbery
oriented containment system instead have
engaged Shawn Povich landscape
architects - we've advised them on that
and they are advised that those shrubs
will do the job and be adequately
irrigated and such so that's a $15,000
recommendation that we came to and you
said that this is potentially the first
in a multi-year plan
yeah but not I suspect that most of not
all of that will be handled by other
grants and by their own resources don't
know that for sure but but in the near
term we're not we're not being asked to
do any more than that landscaping and
such is up to them it would disturb the
vaults
apparently not know I asked that
question - they're gonna be building out
with a lot of soil first so the
embankments like this they'll bring it
out and then do the planting okay
and NYX is a memorial belltower
mechanisms so behind old cheap church
with a graveyard behind you on the left
this is the 75 foot brick tower that you
see and it contains 10 change bills now
Bill's ring in a lot of ways you can
hold the bill bill steady and ring the
clangor you can ring the bell itself
change bells are pulled by ropes and go
up into an open-mouth they call it
position in the sky and then when they
pull the rope again and takes a whole
person pulling down on it the bill comes
down hits the Klang or makes one sound
it goes back up again and that's what
change bills are these are very rare and
very unique they are direct copies of
bills from Hingham England so in 1912
when the town decided to do a memorial
tower for the 275th anniversary of the
town money was collected it was just
donated from everyone in town and they
built this 75-foot Tower and put the
change bells up there the bells are
perfect nothing's happened to them no
one shot at them or anything over the
years they're great but the part they
sit in if you can see the red on the
picture that part has been wearing out
they're open to the air and eventually
that iron gets rusty and they need to be
replaced now out of the ten bells only
to have become very difficult to ring
and bell ringers who really know what
they're doing can barely get them to
work anymore so we're going to start
with these two we know they'll be back
to us in the future for the rest but so
far they're able to ring them and these
are the two they want done they were
made at the Whitechapel Bell foundry in
London which also made the Liberty Bell
and Big Ben so they're very famous
they're wonderful bells of the smallest
one is 550 pounds and the biggest one is
two thousand two hundred and sixty two
pounds they're enormous and wonderful to
hear that sound if you even if you don't
live in that part of town you can hear
the sound when there's church events
town meetings and the rung for all kinds
of things and these bell ringers are a
wonderful group they're part of an
international group that comes to visit
and they trade information and they ring
each other's bells and then you know
it's a terrific group so if somebody
said this may have been the last sound
that our Hingham founders for our town
heard when they left home would have
been the ringing of these bells when
they took off in their ships to come to
America and here we have them the
replicas of them making the same sounds
that's very touching I think so anyway
we we want to help them get up there
with a crane and repair the first two
knowing they'll be back to us over the
years to get the rest on eventually
where will the repairs take place
where's what well where will the repairs
take place the bells don't go anywhere
okay they go up with a crane it'll go
inside take the mechanisms out replace
the mechanisms put the bells attached
again we tried to get them all done at
once this year because we thought once
the cranes there what's the point
sure but they really don't need them at
this point and as you'll see we had lots
of things to do with the money this year
so Mary the question is okay now should
always go ahead just what was the work
that was done to the bell tower within
the past eight or ten years I don't
recall who started the tower itself
started to twist as I understand it
Carolyn the DPW can tell you more about
it but they went in and put a floor of
steel to help it from sort of twisting
and the just the movement of the bells
alone was enough to start to make them
worry about cracks in the in the
building I think Roger Fernandez is here
the bell the bell tower was experiencing
some structural issues in large part
because these bells are very heavy some
of them weigh over a ton and a half and
the tower would sway so we engage the
services of a structural engineer
essentially we've installed a new
structural concrete floor slab if you
were within the building itself that
stabilized the building there were some
additional masonry repairs performed on
the building so the good news is
hopefully the new bells or the repair
mechanisms when they doing them they're
not going to cause the building to sway
roughly so that was what was done and
that was CPC money as well that was CPC
money yep okay thanks now so at one
point in him there were three forts in
town on the highest three hills and one
was up on old fort Street and one was in
the singham Cemetery and still see a
stone foundation up in there and
nobody's quite sure where the third one
was but these were protection for the
town from incoming invasions very early
on so the old fort house after we didn't
need the fort any longer
was moved about half a block downhill
they must have rolled it on logs and set
up as a home and over the years many
people lived there since it was built in
1685 obvious there were lots of owners
over the time but the last owner was our
dear friend John Richardson who
everybody in town knew it was a
wonderful historian in town and saved a
lot of Hingham artifacts in that
structure when he died the building was
going on the market and the Hingham
Historical Society joined up with the
historic Commission to save the building
and you may have all been there but they
put it on a flatbed and they rolled it
down north street and they put it down
on a temporary stone foundation on the
property of the old ordinary until they
had time to figure out where it would go
permanently well now it's time it's been
four years sitting there on this sort of
wobbly Foundation at the time they moved
the fort they also took the cap stones
the giant granite stones that were the
top of the foundation and they've saved
them so this money is too
the old fort house back on its original
Capstone's in a permanent location so
the town can come through and and visit
it it's remarkable inside it has all its
original beams that still have the bark
on them it's just wonderful to see but
they haven't been allowed to let the
tourists go through because it was not
on a foundation so this is really two
parts they will go in first and do a
localized archeological dig to make sure
they're not plopping it down on top of
the grave site or something and then
this will be brought in and put down
permanently on its capstone so I hope
you can see what the picture is that's
the old ordinary the picture on the
right that's kind of bad on there but
the old Ordinaries in the front the big
white areas the parking lot the thing
that looks like a checkerboard off to
the right is the gardens that the Garden
Club maintains and in the red circle in
the back is where the house is sitting
now it probably will be somewhere close
in that area again depending on what the
archaeologists digs up when he's in
there and this is 37,300 sponsored by
the Hingham Historical Society
we had one absentee one abstained on
this vote because he is the treasurer of
the Historical Society the only one that
did not vote for it and my extra is the
harbour walkway extension so you call a
few years ago the trustees a bathing
beach put in that wonderful walk walkway
right running across between the parking
lot at our Harbor and the bathing beach
and that's the picture on the right and
what that looks like now this next
extension being proposed by the Harbor
Development Committee and the bathing
beach trustees will be to take the next
about 360 feet along the harbor till it
gets over to the parking lot for the
boat launch and it's just continuation
of this dream that they've had since oh
seven plan to extend a walkway for bikes
and walkers and strollers and everything
from one end of the harbor to the other
end almost a mile long and 110,000
and will be more than they probably need
for this first extension but as you call
this spring the new bathhouse will be
going in closer to 3a along that picture
on the left and so they'll do whatever
they can with the money we're giving
them but they will either have to get a
grant to finish it or come back to us in
the following year questions the whole
street filled play area as we call it is
an $85,000 recommendation
it's a projected play area as it
indicates not complicated it's on the
site of what used to be a play area with
swings and slides and things but they
deteriorated over the years there's
really nothing left of them now you can
see from the photo on the left it's
essentially a vacant field now it's a
dense relatively densely populated area
down that end of town and they have no
play area in that neighborhood or really
anywhere certainly within walking
distance or bike you know comfortable
biking distance without crossing a lot
of big streets we were told it's the
Recreation Department's top priority
this year to get that done they would
manage it maintain it on their own
budget and they've assured us that if
there are any budget overruns they would
cover that out of their own funds I just
want to thank the recreation Commission
for this you know as you're driving
towards hell you used to go by and see
that and a sad playground equipment and
as you said it's densely populated there
are a lot of families a busy road and it
just seems like this is going to get a
lot of usage and so really appreciate
the Recreation Commission you know
they've been at different ends of town
and finding playgrounds and different
neighborhood playgrounds in different
places all across Hingham if anyone's
looking
see the land it's right past Glastonbury
Abbey on Hill Street
it's on the same side on the left and
all of a sudden you come across this
beautiful pasture and you wonder well
what's that sitting there for it's
that's where the playground will go
Carol - sir question on the location it
tends to flood over the years as part of
the plan to remedy the flooding risk no
it's actually if you look at the land
carefully it's in two layers it with
maybe name queso dip this is on the
block this is the upper level thank you
closest to the street they're gonna
repair the fence that's there so kids
that are playing can't - out into the
street if the lower level is used as
fields once in a while one and as you
say it's not under water okay just a
question triggered in my mind with with
this and others I remember a few years
ago that down at the Harbor with one of
the projects a sign was erected that
said you know this project is being
funded with community preservation as
all these projects advanced well that
signage be put in place it's on their
contract they have yeah that's great
because you know I think they sometimes
as people see this it's a really nice
connection to see where this money is
coming from and not just on this but on
the others we even give them the signs
don't we Carol there's no excuse for not
keeping them up yeah thank you okay okay
the big one I suspect that you all know
as much if not more than I do about this
project when you've all been thoroughly
educated I'm sure but so I'll try to go
through this pretty efficiently we on
the CPC were not only unanimously in
favor of this but I think there was
really no reservations about it and I'll
tell you why
briefly because I know you've heard most
of this if not all of it in a summer or
two there will be no pool in the town
because it's really coming apart and
it's hanging on by by by masking tape
and and should have been replaced long
ago it's I think unjust indisputably
would be a major town asset to have this
facility in place there
currently there is no swim team venue to
practice or to have meets either for the
high school or for the Notre Dame swim
team no indoor pool at all and no pool
period except between the fourth of July
and Labor Day so it's really a
deficiency that is soon going to become
a total deficiency if it's not dealt
with the plan would give us an indoor
year-round lap pool a warm a warm pool
both for relaxation and for therapy and
outdoor family pool looks great for my
grandchildren and I'm sure others its
children to splash around in and an
indoor exercise and multi-use area for
exercise machines lockers showers and
the and the rest and I'm sure it would
do nothing but good for real-estate
values in the town you see realtor's
bringing people over there and showing
them that facility the costs summarized
briefly we allocated or recommended
three hundred thousand dollars for this
project which is somewhat under half of
the estimated construction document
costs of six hundred and fifty thousand
dollars the the reason why there was
there was I think very solid support for
that from a financial point of view is
is largely that there will be no
slippery slope here because that money
will not get spent
unless several contingencies are met one
is that the supporters of the South
Shore Country Club will raise
independently the remaining three
hundred and fifty thousand dollars if
they don't raise the money the allocated
funds go back to the CPC the second
point they would then develop a
long-range plan capital
a financing plan before any construction
goes forward and present that to you and
work that through and get you all
comfortable with that before any of that
money gets spent and if that doesn't
happen and there's not a sufficient
comfort level with that plan then - that
money goes back to the CPC and does not
get spent and the third element is an
operating cost plan that would
reasonably project the revenue to cover
the operating costs the belief at this
point with the help of a outside
consulting firm is that revenues would
be likely to be generated to cover those
operating costs from user fees from
rentals of birthday parties and things
from therapy use of the warm pool and
other sources so to sum that all up we
think it's undeniably a terrific asset
for the town if it came into being we
don't see it as a risk at this point
it's it's essentially a financial
placeholder until they make a case that
convinces us all that the project is
viable financially and we gave them the
full amount they asked for and I would
say as well that we really didn't I
think short change any of the other
applicants to get there we had a
challenging list of requests that was
substantially in excess of the available
money but the weaker projects if you
will kind of dropped along the wayside
before they got to the final stage and
at the final stage nobody got shut out
most of the requests were fully funded
the ones that won't that weren't I think
were adequately funded to do what they
immediately need to do this year so we
don't see this as a an irresponsible
thing at all and that's why we
recommended
yeah you know to your point Jim bill
friend and Jay have come before us a
number of times and sort of kept us up
to speed and I appreciate that because
this is a this is not only a significant
allocation of CPC funds but it would be
a significant project for the town to
undertake so having kept us surprised I
think right along has been has been
helpful and helpful to our decision
tonight I guess my question is with
respect to the three conditions prior to
the expenditure the funds the the vote
language doesn't necessarily designate
that I don't know whether the Advisory
Committee comment would include those
conditions but is there something in
your kind of contractual relationship
with the South Shore Country Club that
would limit that expenditure yeah well
Carol you can speak to it directly if
you like if this is approved CPC puts
together grant agreements and each
project has their own specific contract
and in that contract we will have that
language put in
yeah just a couple things it's it's
interesting of all the different
projects and things on the warrant this
is the one that you know people are
talking about people are asking about
and so I think this is a great
opportunity as well just to confirm a
couple of things that maybe we've known
but as people are starting to get
interested one question I had is if
these construction documents are
prepared what's their shelf life and I
don't know who's best able to answer
that I don't know if it's Jay or Roger
but Jake okay and if you wouldn't mind
coming to the microphone I don't want
dissipate that the drawings themselves
would have an extensive they're short
shelf life right as part of the project
you do there will be a requirement and
take some certain permits local
permitting certainly those permits do
have a shelf life but certainly if the
project were designed we don't
anticipate that you know the year two
years three years down the road that the
drawings would no longer be valid oh and
the only thing that would change that as
if there was a change in the building
code or requirement associated with that
change in the building code that might
necessitate a change in the design Thank
You Roger and Jay maybe you could just
come up because again I think it's
really important that members of the
public understand these conditions so so
the construction document cost is 650
CPC is is going to be paying for 300 of
it but that would not be spent until the
remaining 350 is is already raised yep
so the game plan we have the Friends of
the South Shore Country Club the 501 C 3
that we started in the last six months
here the plan for them is to try to
raise the money by Town Meeting
that's our goal it's a goal obviously
you know but it's clear we need the
three hundred thousand won't get us
anywhere in the construction document
you know world as far as funding for
what we need so we need to raise the
false six hundred and fifty thousand
dollars to move forward and will the
will the work on the construction
documents will there will the financing
plan and the operating cost plan be
required to even begin the construction
document process yeah we I mean
absolutely the conversation we had with
these guys and from our standpoint is
there's no point of spending a dollar of
the three hundred thousand until we're
all comfortable everybody in this room
that that operation and operational and
financial plan makes sense and we have a
clear path of how we'd like to try to
fund this obviously the funding will
come down to Town Meeting but our plan
would be that everyone in this room is
comfortable with at least what that
strategy is well and the revenue
projections you know sort of influence
the design and vice versa yeah you've
got to have some revenue drivers in
there to be able to support the
operation and that's why it's changed
quite a bit over the last year when we
looked at just a six-lane lap pool with
the outdoor family pool financially
speaking it just was it was generated in
a loss when we added the addition of the
warm pool the therapy component along
with the fitness facility it allowed us
to raise our membership fee and also
look at additional revenue from therapy
that brought it to a really good
financial plan I mean still we're at a
point right now where we're tweaking
stuff we're working through potential
opportunities with some different groups
that would lease or a licensed space
from us that would help us with a lot of
that revenue and it would also tie it up
and be more sustainable so if we had
issues with economic downturn and things
like that we exist in contracts in play
that won't change you know that tide is
some serious revenue as part of the plan
so we're still working through a lot of
this the final feasibility study
although we're you know 75% complete
there's still another piece to it that
we need to finalize and that should be
done by the beginning of April hopefully
like April first would be our plan and I
just reiterate that the the plan here is
that this is self-supporting I've had
questions from people who have expressed
concern that this project might compete
for capital dollars for fire stations or
a school
and that's not the case yeah and I mean
I right now we're working on trying to
get the financial plan to be operational
you know in the black obviously there's
a large capital ask or component to it
and that's part of the conversation
we'll have to have with you guys about
how we're gonna move forward with that
you know definitely there's the club has
the availability to take that on through
this project there's definitely a large
fundraising component to it but it may
not cover all the capital needs it will
have to have some sort of conversation
about what we should do with the
remaining but just to then to bring it
back to the original point which is that
the construction documents and that work
will not begin until there is a
financing plan and that financing plan
we're gonna have public discussion about
it so that interested people can come
and participate not a dollar of that
will be spent until we're all on board
with what that financial plan is thank
you I just think that that's helpful
clarity for people who are hearing about
this for the first time it's just and on
a more mundane note what's the what's
the food service component gonna look
like so
Rafael's has the exclusive food and
beverage minimal property so as long as
they're still our food and beverage
provider it will be solely through them
it'll probably be some sort of more
glorified snack shack type of thing but
one thing that we've looked at with the
multi-purpose room is being able to
utilize that row man the evening for
like group corporate meetings and things
like that we've had a lot of success
with that in our function halls and
sometimes the size doesn't fit with what
we currently have so that's something
that we'd be able to do over there as
well to add to the food and beverage
component of it Lucy I don't know if
members of the Advisory Committee of
questions on this project anyone else
from advisory well jay is your hand
raise lots of questions I know that I
may not have all of them tonight but I'm
certainly working to try to get through
them
you Nicole could I just trouble you to
come up to the microphone because that
way people at home can hear your
questions and identify yourself please
sure I'm Nicole Reef Wilson I'm on the
Advisory Committee I'm asking this
question or sort of reiterating some of
the points that have been made just
because as municipal analyst back in the
dark ages of my career I looked at a lot
of feasibility studies and you know they
were four large projects this is a small
project but typically in a feasibility
study you see stress testing on revenue
projections and I guess my one concern
it's you know not as a citizen as a
citizen I love the idea of a pool but I
guess as a finance person my one concern
is that you know health club revenues
are economically sensitive and if we get
into not if when recessions are just
normal things that happen are the
revenues going to be you know so tightly
there that there could be an event where
you're coming to the town looking for
the for money at the same time that the
town's revenues are being stressed by an
economic downturn and you know we have a
deficit at the pool and we have you know
all sorts of potential like tight budget
things that we're dealing with on there
on the other side so I guess I would
want to see a fairly robust feasibility
study talking about the revenues and
what the assumptions are that are going
into memberships and things like that
and and I guess the as an advisory
committee person the first time through
this I would want to see a copy of the
CPC contract that says those three
conditions and then really the fourth
condition being that the capital
financing plan will be in place before
any of the 300,000 has been from the CPC
cuz that's a lot of money to put towards
something if it's not definitely going
to go forward and I would
to think if any of it was spent and it
didn't go forward what kind of feedback
we would be getting about that so that's
a long comment but those are my thoughts
so one part of looking at what you just
mentioned is that when they decide when
they built projections as far as
membership he looked at like the capture
rate you know the area and he went what
I would seem like when we were talking a
fairly low percentage it was like a
three to five percent capture rate of
the area and that's based off
demographics you know age you know what
the population is in the proximity
around the club and the consultant I was
working with thinks that the three to
five percent is a really low target to
look at so there's a lot of room to grow
there and then also when we looked at
building the financial plan you know for
the first three or four years our
utilization we're looking at only like
sixty percent utilization as we watch
the business grow and those are the
years where we generate obviously the
least in the financial plan we have
right now the least revenue you know so
if economic downturn happened I would
like to at least think that in a
business like we're in right now where
the price points a little bit lower than
it is with a higher end private club you
know similar to our golf business where
we're more of like the $50 round golf
instead of the hundred and fifty dollar
round of golf becomes a little bit less
sensitive attack an atomic downturn but
you know hopefully our utilization rates
where we're estimated to be on the low
end to begin with would just stay on the
low end and that would be the worst case
scenario type of thing and then as far
as the fourth point that you brought up
I think that come that the plan that we
have right now and is that we you know
to be able to move forward with the
construction documents we allows us to
be able to buy time with the failing
pool you know like if we were able to
come up with a financial plan that the
selectmen are comfortable with that
advisory thinks makes sense the last
component of that would be the town
voting on it and approving it our plan
would be to hopefully have the
construction documents done by that
point in time in a year from now
basically so that when the town approves
it and that'd be the last piece to that
puzzle we
ready to break ground and start building
a new pool you know in that the reason
why we've set that time line is because
of the failing facility we have and
there's a concern that if we did consign
you know design and build project
together and we don't start that process
until the town approves it in a year
from now or a year plus from now that we
could potentially be you know two years
away from breaking ground at that point
or another year two years from today or
two years from here all the way from
breaking ground so that's kind of why we
structured the timeline the way we did
so that we'd be able to rather than have
a can design build project design get
town needs approval and start building
to help us in that timeline so it's a
different approach and I worked with
Roger to kind of come up with that idea
but it's what I think makes sense based
on the failing structure that we
currently have but then also to speak to
the lard the concern you know up the
whole thing like you know it's the
financial plant has to make sense enough
that you know we don't set ourselves up
for failure and our enterprise fund is
we've solicited I was fortunate enough
to find out and get in contact with the
people that did the feasibility study
for the wellesley pool that they they're
just broke ground on and well you know
it's a much larger project it's like a
20 million dollar project and scope wise
it's different but I got in touch with
the financial group that did the
feasibility study for them and I
contracted them to do peer review on our
financials so I think you know there's a
very small group of people in in the US
that do this recreational financial
analysis and I have two of the most well
known groups looking at the same project
and coming up with I don't know yet what
the peer review numbers will be and what
he'll have to say but by the end of the
day we'll have two groups that analyze
it independently and came up with
hopefully some
and comment
yeah so that's an opportunity like if
you go to the Weymouth Club right now
where you look at there's large like
something like this like digital screens
where you have looped advertising going
on there's an opportunity to sell
advertising so you know facilities like
some of the local high schools the
private high schools in the area of
private elementary schools in the area
that are trying to target groups like us
so when I looked at you know it's
definitely something that we're
interested in it's an opportunity
they're similar to like when you go to
an ice rink you know when you see
advertising around the ice rink and but
it's hard to know you know what the
percent how much money you're gonna make
doing that it all kind of depends on how
hard and how aggressively you work
trying to buy you know sell that
advertising so I looked at what I spoke
with the the gentleman enjoyed the way
him is call up and looked at what they
do in annual advertising and the
different campaigns that they offer and
then also looked at that Wellesley
feasibility study that they put together
and came up with a five percent of gross
revenue is what they desta made as a you
know a campaign that makes sense and a
facility about the size that we have and
that's what I when I put together the
Excel spreadsheet that's what I base it
off is that five percent gross revenue
number you know I have groups members of
my group that I'm working with on this
that think that they could blow that
number out of the water and you know get
her chambers and early block junior up
there you know it's been in you know
thousands of dollars to advertise in our
facility but I tried to push that back a
little bit and say let's just go with at
least what they said in the Wellesley
study the five percent and that's the
number that I used yeah
we will have a chance to ask more
questions when the community
preservation folks come to visit addcom
in a couple of weeks so it's just
nothing else that's urgent I know the
time is passing and you have other
things on your agenda Jay thank you very
much I just had one I guess one other
thought as we as we kind of move forward
and we think about the condition the
conditions and and sort of check back in
with the Board of Selectmen or Advisory
Committee or both
you know the quick notes I took I think
you mentioned that the long range
capital planning would be potentially
subject to consultation with the board
or approval by the board you know the
the the the revenue piece to me is very
important as well and so I just as we
roll forward I wonder if there's a role
for the board to play in terms of you
know added skepticism of of that
analysis so you know as it rolls forward
we may want to think about how we
structure
I guess review of the conditions as we
move forward to to determine whether the
plan makes sense that you know that
that's the guidance that I'm looking for
and I think that we should before we get
you know too deep into that I'd like to
get you the peer review analysis to see
you have both independent you know
things to look at okay yeah I that was
good good to see Quincy yeah Carol or
Jim anything else for for us for this
evening no are you voting tonight or so
you know we we typically on something
like this again and this is I know
you've had your hearings televised which
i think is very helpful for giving all
these great projects visibility but I
think it's this sports practice that
when we have you know some of these
policy decisions will defer the vote for
a week because that gives the
opportunity for the public to ask
questions give input and so next week I
would envision taking this up I don't
you know I I don't envision our having a
lot of conversation but if there is
anyone in the public with the question
or wishes to express themselves so I
think we would probably Tom vote the
both this article next week I just want
to thank you for all your great work I
mean you're um you know I know it looks
all nice and neat clipped together with
the colored pictures but I know there's
been a lot of input a lot of diligence a
lot of other projects that you've had to
make some difficult decisions on and you
know as Mary said at the outset and a
couple of the projects that we got to
talk about because the Board of
Selectmen were involved in them earlier
on you know certain of these projects
really stand out and make Hingham what
it is and so I just on behalf of the
town I appreciate all of your hard work
really do we have a wonderful committee
I just wanted add to that by saying we
wanted to make sure that you were
comfortable with this project I meant
the plural you you've got as I as a
former Advisory Committee Chairman I
have to make that clear as well not just
this 11 but you know in in this process
as as we know in many cases advisories a
proxy for Town Meeting and these are a
lot of questions that might come up on
the floor of town meetings so having the
ability to answer contemplate them be
able to you know talk through them I
just think makes makes the process
easier particularly with this pool this
is this would be a big discussion to
have on the floor of Town Meeting and so
it's it's to everyone's benefit and we
we also appreciate the Advisory
Committee joining us with thoughtful
questions and comments and we will I
think you're going to go back to your
meeting room we're gonna get together
again a week from today for for the
school budget our board still has a
couple of items of business so we would
just thank everybody for this portion of
the evening good to see you all
Thomas as people are just moving out do
we want to just do articles see real
quick
so article C is a perennial article that
covers the reports of the various town
committees we have some language here
that I could propose to the board to
consider you want me to read it
sure so the the article would be titled
reports of various town committees the
articles seem to hear the reports of the
following affordable housing trust audit
committee capital outlay committee
Commission on disability issues
Community Preservation Committee
Conservation Commission Country Club
management committee Council on Aging
Energy Action Committee fire station
building committee ger Hall trustees
Harbor Development Committee
Hingham historic districts Commission
the historian Historical Commission
board of managers of lincoln apartments
LLC long-range waste disposal and
recycling committee the memorial bell
tower committee open space acquisition
committee the scholarship fund committee
the 2006 school building committee
wastewater master planning committee and
the water supply committee order acting
on anything relating thereto these are
the committee's that are formed by Town
Meeting which is why they're
specifically called out as you know in
the annual report we tend to have
reports from all committees as well as
town departments so um and I would just
note that the recommended motion
includes the discharge of the 2006
school building committee which after
consultation with the school committee
and that building committee they said
that their work was completed so that
would that would be part of the
recommended motion to say does that that
has to be voted by Town Meeting right
because it was created I just leave that
convinced right yeah okay so there are
no other bodies that because we've
discharged a bunch of committees but
there are no other committees then
that's always like the the checking that
typo kind of checking okay okay so chief
vote sure about that I moved to
recommend a favorable action on article
C I was presented all those in favor aye
okay I didn't forget that
all right okay no I didn't doubt you
what's that I didn't doubt ya
so the last item on our agenda I'm gonna
turn it over to Karen is an update with
respect to the Hingham Housing Authority
and a discussion about 100 Beale Street
yeah so so shortly after I took office
in May
Tom Mayo Ted Alexa Theotis and I met
with Dave lien Cooper who was then the
chair of the Hingham Housing Authority
to talk about the transfer of about 8
acres of land at on Beale Street so to
to sort of back up about Morrow 17 or 18
years ago there were a bunch of bunkers
used some people in the town right men
might remember in the land that was
around bear Cove Park in this Beale
Street vicinity and those bunker
buildings had asbestos they were a
nuisance you know people were lighting
fires in there and the town determined
that for safety reasons those structures
ought to come down so in the process of
doing the diligence and removing those
structures the town realized that a
couple of the structures were actually
on land about 18 acres of land owned by
the housing authority so the town was
then Charlie cristela who is our town
administrator approached the housing
authority and and suggested that those
buildings need to come down and that the
town could do it but the housing
authority didn't have cash to pay for
that and so the housing authority said
hey well we'll give you some of this
land that we own on Beale Street because
we don't have any need for it and a
certain part of that acreage in any
event is wetlands so I guess there was
about 2001 the town actually entered
into a contract with the Housing
Authority to do just that
we'll take down these couple of
buildings that you know should come down
and you'll transfer to the town about 80
acres of land so in the midst of changes
in town administrators and boards of
select
with all good intentions on everybody's
part the final I didn't get dotted and
the final T didn't get crossed and so
the deed that would actually hand the
land back to the town was never executed
so fast-forward to 2017 2016 27 2017 in
the midst of doing some diligence around
the parcels owned by the selectmen on
Peel Street I think it was part of the
board's earlier discussions of the
development of the Beale Street property
prior to the Alliance project coming
online through Town Council Susan Murphy
we did some diligence on you know what
do we own were the property lines what
are the conditions you know the kind of
stuff you'd go through if you're gonna
undertake development of your property
so when doing that it came to the town's
attention that indeed this eight acres
that that we were supposed to get as
consideration for taking down those two
old buildings never came to the town and
so this past summer as I said the
beginning I talked to David lien Cooper
made her aware of this omission and
talked with her about making sure that
we finalized this transaction
you know the buildings have come down
about eighteen years ago and so now
let's just finalize things so we engaged
in some conversations over the summer
and into the fall
Dave lien talked with her her board
Susan Murphy and I went to a Housing
Authority board meeting to explain what
we had found to present the board again
with the contract that had been signed
with the town
to convey the land and the and the
Housing Authority board requested some
additional diligence materials which
were in line with exactly what I would
ask for if I were being asked to
consummate this transaction
you know contracts and actually evidence
that the buildings came down copy the
contract so that you can as a fiduciary
for the housing authority check that off
your list we provided all of that stuff
to Dave Lee and Cooper again as the then
chair the house
authority she found it all in order the
pro bono attorney I understand that
works works with the housing authority
on other housing matters found it all in
order and so the housing authority was
scheduled to take a vote to transfer the
property and to execute the deed in
favor of the town for this eight acres
the housing authority instead took a
vote not to transfer this land back to
the town I guess at this time and that
was a three to one vote by the housing
authority so it puts us in a little bit
of a dilemma I think we have we have
patiently sort of worked through an
issue that we discovered with the
housing authority trying to correct
something that should have been
corrected years ago I I don't dispute
that and we sort of patiently worked
through our process I worked through it
on behalf of the board as your liaison
my role tonight was to report out how I
did with that project which wasn't too
well I guess but to tell you that we're
now in a situation where the Housing
Authority has a parcel of land that
really belongs to the town so I think
we're in a position I guess you know
from my personal standpoint we're in a
position where we need to decide what
steps we would take to move forward to
get back an asset that belongs to the
town the thing that's a little the thing
that makes it a little uncomfortable is
that you know the Housing Authority is
part of us even though it's a state
agency with its own elected board
it's in Hingham the people who live
there are in hang them you know the
volunteers are hanging residents so it's
this discussion tonight's a little
uncomfortable that notwithstanding that
you that not was standing this is a
promise that the Housing Authority board
made to the town the town undertook work
on the basis of that promise and what
we're asking the Housing Authority to do
is fulfill its promise so
I think that I guess there's a couple
couple approaches we could take to this
we could sort of set a time line to say
now that you sort of fully understand
the scope of this issue and the response
that the town actually needs to take to
get the land back you know would the
Housing Authority consider or reconsider
its vote and actually effectuate the
deed has a promise to do in its contract
or you know and I hate to say this or
the other alternative is that the town
would be in a position where we would
have to sue its own Housing Authority it
would have to seek a declaratory
judgment for specific performance in
Superior Court my in the Orlan Court so
unfortunately that's where where where
we're at with this and I don't know if
I've done it justice or a few have
additional questions but that's my
report I was on the housing authority
when they entered into this agreement
with the town yeah I can't read it and
Griffin right you got to hit the mic Jim
Jim if you wouldn't mind so that the
view and I should know better the u.s.
who was on the authority at the time yes
yep Jane Davis was the chair at the time
John Cafferty who was to say too pointy
and Griffin who I think was a tenant
myself and right now I don't remember
who else I'm going by the people who
sign the agreement Bob keys yeah Bob
keys I thought I said that right so the
remaining ones at Bob keys and myself
those people have been all along and
who's on the housing authority presently
hey now don't move down to three people
because of devil his resignation and
because of the tenant vacancy so it's
myself Bob and Irma locker
this was the state of pointy just three
people and see under the if I could just
expand on this under the open meeting
law we can't talk to each other at all
we feel your pain what we feel your pain
excuse me yes and so that when did
dabble in Cooper resign about a week
he'll after the after the meeting that
went badly and I think she there's a lot
of issues she has you know three various
reasons but very well thought out but
spend about a week any other questions I
just want to make sure I understand the
lay of the land
thank you you've you've invested a lot
of time in this as his attorney Murphy
and you know appreciate it and I share
with you that we're sort of in an
uncomfortable spot and I guess my point
of view and you know you mentioned that
you know in in these different
situations we all have fiduciary
responsibilities and it's often
difficult when you have boards the
turnover and things are uncovered and
you know we were we were not on the
original board that that enacted a
transaction but that's really where I
think we have to rely on you know the
documentation and and Town Meeting votes
and I guess I look at it and say that we
have a fiduciary responsibility to the
town which is you know I know we all
take that seriously and I know the
housing authority takes it seriously you
know what what I might propose to my
colleagues is that this this has been
helpful while Thomas kept a surprised
it's helpful to hear this
I think it's been our board's practice
that we typically don't you know when we
get a report out on something we
typically don't necessarily vote on
something the night of a meeting I know
I sort of like to reflect on this and I
would maybe suggest that that would
provide you know I would propose a
two-week window at which it would also
provide the housing authority with an
opportunity to Rican
it's vote if it chose to so I might
suggest that we put this on our agenda
for two weeks from now which is February
13th if if that's agreeable to my
colleagues and I can provide you with
you know if you want the diligence
package that we put together for the
housing authority I can provide you with
that so you can sort of step through and
see exactly the decision timeline and
and to your point Mary the property
rights of the town that we really have
no we really have no we have no
alternative here we need to perfect the
property rights of the town yeah you you
just said what I was going to ask for it
you know because of the Open Meeting Law
we can't talk to each other and what is
going to request was a deferral of any
action to give us a chance to have a
couple this one special meeting where
the three of us can talk
I can't guarantee any results from it
sure to do that and what my purpose of
that would be to review you know all the
issues around the site the current
issues and to identify the actions that
we need to take to bring about the
conveyance many of us thought wrongly
that that had been done and that it just
hadn't been recorded for some reason and
that was so like a little folklore
within the authority that all yeah
nobody recorded it well we we didn't
take the steps needed and I talked to
Sharon a director today and she was
saying right we don't necessary have the
capacity to draft that deed and do the
things that are needed but in 2001 we
agreed to do these things and it's
finding it's still binding and uh so
anyway it sounds like what we're
proposing would would would be you know
that that would that would work as well
and I appreciate your coming tonight
oh yeah and let me just offer that you
know the night we met with you all in
December when Susan Murphy and I were
with you we indicated that Ms Murphy
would draft a deed that the Housing
Authority board could execute in
addition MS Murphy has drafted the
necessary vote that the board would need
to take to effects we effectuate the
transfer so we
we get that you don't have potentially
the legal bandwidth and we are you know
we offered it we have those materials I
can make that available to you tomorrow
I also want to say Jim that you've been
very diligent and very thoughtful since
we've I think been able to talk further
about just what this means and and you
know I guess I think it's important I
know there's like a lot of noise around
some of some of this transaction you
know there's been a lot of noise about
development on Beale Street I really
think in this case and I said this to
you when we chatted on the phone a
couple times late last week this is a
very narrow legal issue and that I
really think you got to put the noise
aside and you've got a you've got to
look at what the legal obligation is of
the housing authority to the town of
Hingham and we can deal with some of
this other stuff later and and continue
to have conversations about the concerns
that have arisen around the parcel
itself
but the legal obligation is the key to
this particular transfer I'm afraid I
don't get everything that you're saying
I mean I'm not just hearing it's
activity but I guess acting chair by
default or something that I totally
respect that I was here I was with the
media machalek resettled we totally
agree to it and we went sort of into a
passive mode and didn't write right and
we're talking to Sharon tonight director
just saying we don't really have these
staff capacity to know and bring about
all the steps and I'm saying okay fine
let's have a couple special meetings
identify what is needed and I think you
were saying that perhaps you are the
resources we can get that tomorrow we
can get that to tomorrow Jim we can get
you the the things that you need to get
this done we can give you tomorrow good
you think very quickly yeah okay okay
and that's good because after that takes
away one impediment right yeah I'm sorry
I gonna get here I think I get an echo
it's hard it's echoing in here when this
we'll get you it yeah we'll get you what
you need we'll get you what you need a
chance thank you thank you Jim I
appreciate it I appreciate I am I am
gonna put this on for two weeks I'm soso
February 13th I mean as you know and you
and your you're good at always coming to
our meetings and sitting through but
particularly this time of year with
warrant articles and other things like
that we we have a number of things the
board wants to take up so it would be my
intent to take this up on the 13th it's
two weeks yeah thank you thank you
thanks Jim yeah Jim if I may can you
hear me okay Jim I've known you a very
long time I believe you to be an
honorable man I respect your strength of
character coming in tonight for this
very difficult conversation I say I
think that sets you in a special place I
urge you to provide you to prevail upon
your colleagues to recognize the
difficult conversation that you've just
had with us and and take the necessary
steps to correct well we will just call
a hiccup so that we can go forward and
continue to work together collegiately
thank you Jim
thanks Jim appreciate it watch the cord
okay
don't trip yeah thank you okay and I
would suggest Karen if you've got that
if you've got that information to maybe
give it to Tom to circulate that would
be that would be helpful I think
actually I'm just double-checking I
think we've concluded theater for this
evening so we will next meet a week from
tonight
and a portion of our meeting will be
business with with the board we will in
this room have the joint school budget
hearing with the School Committee the
Advisory Committee and our board and so
we thank everybody for joining tonight I
accept a motion to adjourn so moved
Jim our next meeting is on next Tuesday
February 6 given and 13 February 13th
take a motion to adjourn so moved second
all those in favor all right
good night everybody thank you
you